Luke, a subquery is a
query inside of a query,
similar to how the
force is inside of you.
Watch this video on subqueries in case
your whole Jedi gig doesn't pan out.
May the force and subqueries
be with you always.
And cut. Oh boy, that was the worst
job ever. We need better actors.
Would somebody please see if Fidel
is available? We need to up our game.
Nobody's going to want to learn
SQL unless these videos improve.
Welcome back to Module 8 on Subqueries.
Subqueries are so important
that even Luke Skywalker himself
may be learning subqueries just
in case the whole Jedi thing
doesn't work out. This is on the
screen a photo of Hannah Davies.
She's a former colleague, student
of yours. We were in Clearwater,
Florida, where she helped give
a conference presentation.
And I just happened to have
the Data Fundamentals book
in our snorkeling gear, along
with my daughter, Megan.
Megan's on the boat, and I posed
this question to her, to Megan.
Hey, do you want to hear about
self-contained surgeries?
No.
Sorry. and Megan did not want to
hear about self-contained subqueries
but that's what we're going to
cover today and they're called self
-contained subqueries and just as
Vader said a subquery is a query
inside of a query and that's what
makes it a subquery a query inside
of a query but they're also called
self-contained subqueries and I'll
show you what that means in just a
minute and And then in the advanced
class, 5310, we do a different kind
of subquery called a correlated
subquery, which is not self
-contained. Your deliverables for this
week include the blue triad, which
again is to follow along with
code, copy the code into Word document
as we go through the video, and
upload that just to show that you
are following along. We also have
an animation on a topic called Exist,
and Exist is a type of subquery
that uniquely stops once a single
value that it's looking for
becomes true. And we'll have more
about that, of course, later in a
different video. Part of that exists
animation also has an associated
quiz that goes along with it. Again,
you can retake the quiz as many
times as you need in order to get
100%. And then if you're on campus
Thursday, we'll have the lab. If
you're online, then the second part
of the week you'll work on lab
four based entirely on subqueries.
All right we'll start out with
the blue triad and this goes back
to module seven on joins. Here's
the problem for you to solve and
we're using the university data
set for this particular module.
Using a joined lists the
last name of students that
have a locker in building
B and go ahead and pause
the video and try to Solve
that problem on your own.
This is similar to a problem
that you'll have on the exam.
Let's take a look at it.
Here's the solution. We have
select S. S is the alias for
student, S dot last name.
From student is S, join Jim Locker is
GL. We put the two tables together.
On S dot student ID is equal to GL
dot student ID, then the predicate
logic where GL, where the business
where the locker location is building
B and so this is the solution to the
blue triad number one and that is
using a join now we have two different
sub queries that we're going to
cover today one of them and the first
one we'll tackle is a type 2 sub
query and the typing is is is my
way of categorizing these two types
of sub sub queries and by type 2 what
I mean is the subquery will derive
information from two or more different
tables, and so to do a type 2
subquery, you would ask yourself, is
my output from one table, which you
can see in this case is true, it's
from the student table, and do I
need information from another table,
for instance, the gym locker, in
order to solve this problem? So if
the answer to both of these are true,
then it could be a subquery that
you use in order to solve that
problem. So let's take a look at the
subquery and compare it to a join.
And one of the things, there's
some amazing videos on YouTube, but
very few really demonstrate the
difference between a subquery
and a join is very small. In fact,
in some ways it's the way that
you're writing the code, the way
that you're presenting the code.
If we look at the traditional
join, remember we have
two parts. One are which
tables you're going to
join. and then two is the
primary foreign key link.
A subquery needs both of those
pieces of information, which
tables, and then the primary
foreign key link. However,
when you write the select last name,
and because we say from student
only, you don't need to have the
alias and you don't need the alias
up here. So this starts out similar,
select student from last, excuse
me, select last name from student.
And then the WHERE clause is
where our subqueries for this class
are going to take place. So in the
WHERE clause is where we're going
to indicate the second part of a
join, which is which primary foreign
key links are we interested in.
So we'll initially say WHERE student ID,
and think of the join.
We have student ID.
IN is going to be the link
between the outer and the
inner subquery. so in and
after the word in then we
start our subquery with the
parentheses the word select
and then the next item would be
that foreign key primary key link so
if we say where student id in
select almost every time for us it's
going to be student id so if you
think about the where clause student
id and student id represents that
part of the join it's just written
a little bit differently and it's
written after the end statement
and then we would indicate from and
the second table where in the join
we join both tables on one line
here we write the initial from the
student table we do the primary
foreign key link and then we have from
the gym locker which would be
the second table after that the
information we need is from another
table being the gym locker table we
can end with our predicate logic
where the locker location is equal
to building b now there is a
difference between a scalar and multi
-valued subquery. And for this class,
the difference for us is just going
to be this. If you see an equality
symbol here, an equal symbol, we
know that we want just one row
returned from the inner query to the
outer query. If it's multi-valued,
think of n or anything else,
greater than, less than, all of those
would be great for a multi-valued
subquery. And that just means
you expect more than one piece of
information, more than one row to be
provided back. And I'll show you in
SQL in just a minute, but what's
happening is this inner query runs.
It provides the results to the
outer query, similar to our
in that we learned earlier in
the semester when we did single
table joins. So let me demonstrate
this over in SQL Server.
I copied this code from the PDF
document, and the PDF document
was made in Microsoft PowerPoint.
And I just want to show you,
if you create something in
PowerPoint or in Word, it will have
apostrophes with this fancy
curve to it. And if it does, then
that code just doesn't work. If
you double-click on the error
message, it shows there's some
kind of problem up here. And in
that case, it just is referring
to that fancy parenthesis or
apostrophe, which needs to be just
plain like TXT document. Okay,
let's take a look at what
we have here. We have
select last name from
student, where student ID in.
This is where the subquery will
begin. We have the primary key,
the in link, the parentheses,
and then we start the subquery.
Now, in the Ben Ghosn book, he
does talk a bit about how to format
your code, and there are some
conventions. I'll let you go ahead and
read that. In our class, we're not
critical about code. It should follow
a fairly logical pattern, but each
company is going to have its own
standards for how the code
should be written, and so we're
fairly flexible on that. There
are some common conventions.
The keywords select from where
are all completely capitalized
and so forth. And some of it
is just for convenience of
tabbing in and making the code
a little bit more readable.
Looking forward to the exam,
though, you'll want to make
sure that any code that you
write, don't worry about spaces
or tabs. Sometimes that can
cause the exam, the proctorio,
and everything to fail when
you're doing coding questions.
All right. So with this, let's
take a look at what's happening.
We have this inner query, and earlier
I called this a self-contained.
subquery. If I run this query,
you can see that it provides this
information, a number of different
rows, and what this is doing
technically is it's providing this
information back similar to if
we had just said where student ID
in and then 6 comma 39 comma 33
and so forth and if we put all of
those in that would be the same.
Now when this runs the inner query
when it feeds this information
to the outer query it does automatically
distinct in the inner query.
So you technically don't have to
do distinct in the inner query.
However, to make both a join and
a subquery the same because joins
don't use distinct, you may have to
use distinct in the outer subquery
because that's not automatically
or default going to be considered
distinct. And so we have this
information, what's happening. So
effectively, we take the inner query
and we provide that information.
It's self-contained again
because it can run on its own. It
provides that to the outer
query, and that is conceptually
how a type 2 subquery works.
All right, based on what we
just did, let's take a look
at another blue triad. Show me
student's last name that received
an award from 2010 to 2023.
And I have some of the code
set up for you. And you'll also
need to solve code on the
main page, again, for Canvas.
We do have the diagrams, but
you'll need to have the diagrams
so you can see which table
or tables we're connecting.
So go ahead and stop the
video if you want to try this.
Here's the code for the
blue try it, number two.
We have select last and first
name of students that received
an award. So from the student
table, this is the output
from one table. We do need
information from another
table. So we notice that the
primary foreign key between the
student table and the student
award table is student ID.
So we'll use where student ID in
and then select. and some of the
exam questions might even ask you
what is the what's most likely going
to go after this inner select
statement and the answer would be
whatever is after the where statement
in this case student id from
the new table student award and
then we have the predicate logic or
award year between 2010 and 2023
so go ahead and paste that into the
document that you're creating the
blue triad and then let's cover
a type one sub query and i think what
i'll do is i'm going to introduce
type 1 subquery so that you
have a initial introduction to a
type 2, initial introduction to a
type 1, then I'll stop that video.
And then in video 2 I'll primarily
have examples of different
subqueries, type 1 and type 2, along
with subqueries that use three, four,
five different levels of subquery.
So referring to four or five
different tables. All right, a type
1 subquery is one where I don't have
you do a join before it because
this type of subquery it requires
a subquery. And I call it a type
1 because you just have one table
that you're dealing with. And in
this case, we have, as you can see,
in fact, let me highlight
this, and I'll copy this over
and bring SQL Server. And
let me show you what I think
makes sense. And this is where
students miss it on the exam sometimes.
So we have select cash prize and
description from award, where cash
prize, and I think we want is
greater than the average cash price?
Well, you know based on doing
aggregate functions, you don't write
out the full word average, but you
could say average cash price, and we
run this, and the challenge is it
looks pretty good where cash price
is greater than the average cash
price. Which table are we referring
to? Only the award table. That's
all we've got. But if you run it,
it says that you can't
use an aggregate in the
WHERE clause unless it's
contained in a subquery.
So this is where a type 1
subquery would come into effect.
You don't simply repeat it
like we did for the type 2, but
what you would do is after
this greater than is start your
inner query, which if I said
show me the average cash price
from the award table, just that,
you would likely say select
average cash price from award
and we have to close that off.
On the exam you don't
have the IntelliSense
showing that you properly closed it off.
And let's run this code
and now it's perfect. What this is
showing is any of the awards that
happen to be greater than the
average award and by average again we
mean the mean. Where these are
all going to be self-contained, at
least for the subqueries, you can
highlight that inner query. It takes
this information, the 52.2, and
that's where, on a question, if it
says don't hardwire, what it's asking
for is a subquery. If you hardwire
it, you would type in 52.2, and
you try to run this, and it would
work just fine. It's just think
about transaction systems where you
have your data are changing all
the time and so this would be a way
not to hardwire it but to use that
inner query so in this case it did
require a subquery it's a type
one and so you don't have a choice
on the exam if it says write a query
and it doesn't tell you join or
subquery you can decide but make
sure if it says write a join you
write join code if it says write a
subquery you write subquery code and
in this case if it's a question
like this that shows greater than
the average or $10 greater than
something, you'd have to use a subquery
because you can't have an aggregate
function in the where clause.
That's a no-no.
All right, I'm going to pause
the video here and come back
with a second video just so
we can break these videos
into a little bit smaller
chunks for you, and I will see
you in subqueries part two where
we'll go into more detailed
subqueries and we also cover
a topic called substring.
We'll see you in just a few.
For more information visit www.fema.gov